Finding Aid for Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch records, 1938-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch records 1938-2005
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch.
1 oversize volumes
1 linear feet
86355 Bj 2
Correspondence, minutes, newsletters and newspaper clippings concerning activities of the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti branch of this anti-war organization; also collected materials from the state chapter and from local branches in Detroit, Ingham County, Oakland County, Rouge Valley, and Traverse City, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by different officers of the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti branch of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Donor no. 4595 ) in several accessions beginning in 1968.
The record group is open to research.
The Women's International League for Peace and Freedom was founded in 1915 while the United States was debating its possible involvement in World War I. The League, through the work of its members, was opposed any American participation in the war. Members of the League traveled to the Hague in 1915 where they met with women from other countries and made proposals on how to end the war. After the war the League continued to call for peaceful resolutions to conflicts in the United States and abroad. With the onset of the Second World War, the organization persisted in its efforts to strive for and maintain a peaceful society.
The activities of the group did not cease with the close of the Second World War. During the period of the Cold War, the group campaigned for an end to the production and further development of nuclear weapons. In 1948 the Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch was founded to support this and the other causes of the national branch of the Women's League. The new group's bylaws articulated three objectives. The first of these objectives was to promote military non-violence for the United States and social non-violence between the races and classes. Its next objective was to help carry out the policies of the national branch by outwardly supporting those positions in the Ann Arbor community. Finally, it sought to develop educational programs at the state and national levels, through legislation, that would help WILPF carry out its goal of global non-violence.
In the 1960s the Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch shifted its involvement from local issues to international issues when debate over the conflict in Vietnam escalated. The members of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom were encouraged to write to their congressional representatives in Washington and persuade them to stop supporting the Vietnam conflict. Locally, the organization became vocal in their opposition to the war. Public interest in the group began to grow as its anti-war position became more popular. To increase public support for its position, the group held lectures, wrote op-ed pieces in the Ann Arbor News, led demonstrations and held fund raisers to support its efforts financially. When the Vietnam conflict ended, the organization shifted its interests back to more local issues. The group protested against some policies and practices of the City of Ann Arbor. It believed the city maintained unfair housing practices that discriminated against minorities. In another local fight the group protested a decision by the University of Michigan Regents to change its policy on research which could result in the loss of human life. Besides local causes, the group continues to remain active on national issues such as NAFTA, ensuring better race relations, crusading for abortion rights and the clean-up of the environment.
The records of the Ann Arbor-Ypsilanti branch of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom document the various causes espoused by the League, notably its opposition to the Vietnam conflict and to the Gulf War. Locally, the group promoted education with its Jane Addams Book Award, worked closely with UNICEF, and fought for fair housing practices. These activities are also documented within the files. The League records show the group's continuous community involvement. The records are arranged into three series, Alpha File, Michigan Branch and Other Michigan Branches.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Ingham County (Mich.); Oakland County (Mich.); Peace--Societies, etc.; Traverse City (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.); Women and peace.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Ann Arbor - Ypsilanti Branch.
- Alpha File 1941-1996
  The Alpha File (1948-1996) series makes up the bulk of this collection. The local newsletter that they produced was mostly a tool for the group to promote their meetings, and lectures and to keep members updated on fund raising and the causes for which they were raising funds. The newsletters also provided members with information about how to contact their representatives in Washington, and how those representatives voted on issues that were important to the group. The collection documents the group's work on their community projects such as the Jane Addams Children's Book Award and UNICEF. The correspondence revolves mostly around the organization writing to officials at the United Nations and in the U.S. government, including Senator Philip Hart and former Presidents Gerald Ford and Jimmy Carter.
  - Annual Reports, Resolutions 1953, 1961, 1968, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1948-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Fliers and Programs 1953-1996 (Box 1)
  - Jane Addams Children's Book Awards 1953-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ledger 1951-1961 (Box 1)
  - Local Involvement-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Member -- Biographical (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1958-1995 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1948-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - National Involvement-Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Newsclippings 1959-1996 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters 1962-1996, 1999-2005, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook (Volume 1)
  - Songs (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's Manuals and Financial Reports 1956-1975 (Box 1)
  - UNICEF Miscellaneous 1972-1975 (Box 1)
- Michigan Branch 1953-1975
  The Michigan Branch (1953-1975) contains collected materials, mainly minutes and resolutions from the state meetings, bulletins, financial records and membership records. The bulletins kept members of different branches updated on state meetings and what the Michigan branch, as a whole, was doing. The bulletins also served to keep Michigan members in touch with the national interests of the organization.
  - Bulletins 1960-1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records 1963-1970 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Announcements, Programs 1955-1965 (Box 1)
  - Membership Records 1964-1968 (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1953-1974 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Resolutions 1963-1965, undated (Box 1)
- Other Michigan Branches 1938-1975
  The third series, Other Michigan Branches (1938-1975), includes scattered minutes, clippings, newsletters, and financial records from five different Michigan branches. The branches include Detroit, Ingham County, Oakland County, Rouge Valley, and Traverse City.
  - Detroit Branch 1960-1975 (Box 1)
  - Ingham County Branch 1962-1966 (Box 1)
  - Oakland County Branch 1956-1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Rouge Valley Branch 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Traverse City Branch 1938-1965, 4 folders (Box 1)